today we're going to demonstrate how to
take a public domain comic book
take a story out of it clean it up
and prayer parrot for re-lettering with
Cherokee
this purpose of this is to use
already existing material to reduce the
amount of Labor
and how long it takes to produce new
educational material for use by students
Comics are a real good medium
for teaching languages because a lot of
the story is done graphically and does
not require descriptions in language
the only thing that's really
um
translatable or it needs to be
translated and put into the target
language is the dialogue which is
actually a more important component of
language and learning okay the first
single thing we need to do is to
actually get a
comic book and download it so that we
can get the images for the pages out of
it
um in this particular case we are going
to be using
um
a portion of the comic book series Billy
and buggy bear
um a
a group of students and teacher have
been translating it into Cherokee so
it's a good starting point
to
demonstrate how to take what they've
done as far as translation work goes and
to
repurpose a comment with re-lettering in
Cherokee
so the first thing we've got to do is
we've got to go do a site such as
comicbookplus.com there are other sites
available but this one is one of the
easier ones that we have found to use
so I want to search for Billy and muggie
Bear
and here it is and it'll actually show
multiple
um like setups for it so we'll just
click on the first one here okay
the particular one that they are
translating from is Billy and buggy
Bearer issue number 10.
so we'll go to that so now we have issue
number 10 being displayed so what we
need to do now is to download the file
so I want to place it into a folder I've
already created myself a folder called
comics and inside that I've been created
another folder called Billy and Boogie
Bear the file will end with cbz this
means compressed comic book zip
so we'll go ahead and save it there
as soon as it's saved
we can close out the web browser
and we come over here
and so here is the file so now I can
right click the file on here and tell it
I wish to extract it
Windows machines and MAC machines
probably do that a little bit
differently but it should be very
similar to what I'm doing here with my
Linux box
so now I can go into this folder
now so as you can see each page
is an image so like for page one
or image one is the cover page
so image two this is an ad that was in
the comic
um from based on this they've skipped
the inside of the cover because it's
probably blank
and like here we have the first story in
this particular comment Pat and Mike in
this clear case we're looking for
um specifically salty turtle
in this
here
so let's take a look at the actual page
so what you're looking at is the first
to keep in mind is that Comics
especially in the 40s and 50s
and probably all the way up through the
90s and even modern Comics to some
degree were printed on a thin cream
paper so this is why this isn't white
aging of the paper additionally has
occurred which makes it even darker
so that's one of the things we have to
correct for
um in this particular case we'll be
removing all of this paper color right
here because we don't want it we want it
to be transparent so that it doesn't
impact anything we're doing
and it's the same thing for here
and here
for the speech bubbles and
things like we know for a factor must be
white we normally just remove that and
put a white true white in so that it
um displays better in modern printing
for paper Printing and displays better
in ebook readers
one other thing that normally has to be
handled
depending upon your needs is the removal
of English writing from various portions
of the text
this particular case there's English
writing
in the image on the book that's one
thing that has to be corrected
um
is usually a few but not many this way
for example this wanted poster also has
English writing on it that will need to
be removed
and I'll show you how one way of doing
that there's not a
set way but there is a way and I can
show you how I go about doing it so I
have a program called [ __ ] installed and
I use it
for
um Graphics manipulation so this is the
main program here
and I will go ahead and open up
number 29 which is the first image of
the story we're wanting to do here I can
have a preview so now I'm looking at the
right one
and I can hit open
now [ __ ] normally saves things in a
format called xcf so that's the first
thing we need to do is to save this as
xcf so I just hit file save as it's
already going to put the xcf on the end
and the rest of the name is going to be
the same so I can do that it's going to
be in the same location that I'm pulling
from which is fine for now and I can hit
save
so now I have a way to save my changes
as a work in progress okay the first
thing we need to do is to apply what's
called level adjustments
um
it's kind of the black really isn't
black
and we would like to get a better
contrast in the intensity of the colors
before we start
so we go to so we go to colors
levels
so what we're going to look at is the
input levels we're going to leave the
output levels to 0 and 255.
what we're going to need to do is if you
look at this waveform right here this
represents where
the visual range of the images so if I
can sit here and I can grab this one and
I can move it over
like that
and if you notice the black actually
turns black
and gives in all the colors actually
become enhanced
then we can move this one down just a
little bit
to get rid of the washout some
and we can probably move this up a
little bit more
say about there so make a note of these
numbers because we want to apply the
exact same settings
to any future pages from the same scan
of the same comic book each comic book
that you do will have to be this will
have to be recalculated each time as
each version of the comic book was going
to be slightly different due to aging
Etc so in this particular case I
selected 45 and here right here you can
see where you can actually
pick a collar that you want to be
treated as black and here you can pick a
colors you want to treat as white so
let's go ahead and do that so you can
see how that works we'll click this one
here
well first we'll um zoom in so we can
see better
what we're doing and then we're going to
um
tell I want
this to be my black
and then I want to tell it I want
this to be my white
Zoom back out
and I can see what and see how it looks
so that actually does improve it a
little bit better now you can see where
the paper was original color the paper
most likely was probably like this and
here you can see the Aging of the paper
whereas the darker areas
so let's go ahead and use these values
then
um which would be
and 217.
okay now that that's done
the next thing we need to do is begin
removing
portions that need to become transparent
okay the next step we need to do is we
need to add a transparency layer the
reason we need to add a transparency
layer is because to remove this stuff
and have it become transparent so that
it's not anything not even you know
neither white nor black nor anything
it allows anything below it to show up
we have to add a special layer for that
jpegs by default do not
work with transparency options you have
to add it okay for the transparency uh
that's a two-step process first we need
to select this which is the image
this is a layer of You by the way so we
hit layer and the first thing we're
going to do is add what's called an
alpha Channel this allows this
particular component to be see-through
to the layer below it so we're going to
first hit add Alpha Channel
then we're going to hit the add layer
button we don't need to worry about
naming it we just need to make sure the
fill width says transparency
and then hit OK then we need to change
the order so this layer needs to get
moved down below this layer
so once we've done this as a
demonstration
you can now make it transparent method
of removing things from this image it's
important to have the layer you're
working with selected in this case in
every case it's going to be the jpeg
layer
so now I can select the um
fuzzy select tool
which will allow me to select areas for
removal based upon similar colors
um and I can increase the amount of area
being selected for removable by
pulling the mouse down and I can reduce
the amount of area selected for removal
by moving the mouse up this is while I
have the left Mouse button clicked so
when I do this what I'm going to be
doing is I'm going to click and hold
and then I'm going to pull down
and I'm going to watch
for any areas that get removed I don't
want remove as soon as I see that which
is like right here I'm seeing areas that
I want removed
I need to go back up
to where they're put back
something like that then I need to hit
delete button and now you can see where
the paper uh will go the cream paper has
been removed from the image now I need
to zoom in
because here we have some more areas
that need to be removed so I'm going to
click and hold I'm going to pull down
then I'm going to hit delete button and
I will repeat here
and I can repeat here
zoom out make sure I didn't mess
anything up
it all looks good
now if you look you'll you'll see little
spots like that
and one of the things that can be done
is I can click right here
and then I can start pulling down
and it will get more spots that way
that is not what I wanted
there's whenever that becomes a problem
I'm hitting Ctrl shift a to deselect
everything whenever that becomes a
problem where when you're trying to
remove it and it just won't let you
um most of the work's already done with
what I was wanting removed so what I'm
going to do now is I'm going to take
the rectangle selection tool
and I'm going to select
up to next to the image there
I want to hit delete
and I'm going to go
do the same thing on this side I'm going
to get as close as I can
without actually touching anything
and I'm going to hit the delete button
onto the bottom
and I'm going to repeat
I don't want to do it for this section
here like this
and this doesn't have to be perfect by
the way it has got to be good enough to
help with
the next steps which is just getting it
mostly cleaned up
all right so the next thing I need to do
is now we have all this extra space at
the bottom
now that we really don't need
um
but we'll take care of this
um later we need to kind of keep the
page size consistent
and we can we'll look at how to do that
later
all right so I'm going to save my work
so far
It's always important to do that
then we're going to go to the speech
bubbles
so I'm going to go back to my fuzzy
select tool
and then I'm going to be like that you
can see now that most of the speech
bubble has been cleared out then I can
go to here to this one which is called
the free select tool and I can actually
draw
like this
very carefully
not to go back to where it started from
it'll dot will light up then I can let
go
I'm going to press delete
and then I can press Ctrl shift a to
make the selection go away to see if
there's any spots left there is
do like that
remove that final spot
so now I have a clear speech bubble
which I can then
use to re-letter later
we'll repeat
um
same thing here
zoom in so I can see what we're doing
better
control day
oops
Fuzzy's leg
free select
so the speech bubble has been totally
cleared out next up is actually optional
I have a tendency to want to remove any
English from the
um Comics I'm re-lettering which
includes things like the title
and again seeing English where it's
feasible sometimes it's just really not
very feasible and then later we can put
in a different font in Cherokee for the
title and the same thing for here
we'll be using inkscape to do the second
part the first part here which we're
using with just [ __ ] is strictly
for cleaning up the images
so as you can see we're going to have
two sections that are going to need
adjustment
and there's two ways to go about doing
this I can either do it totally in
inkscape or I can do it
or I can remove the text using in what
they call endpaint functions and like
the same thing for here
so that I have a clean template to work
with in inkscape and that's what we're
going to do on this one because and it's
mainly because of the
um the amount of texture to be easier
when we put it in inkscape to re-letter
when we uh if we don't have all this up
here that we have to hide using inkscape
if this actually does not end the image
at all so what we're going to do is
we're going to go to here
and we're going to go to clone
smudge clone tool so what we're going to
do is we select what we want to clone
from
okay you have to control click
and you can see over there on the right
that
the button where I control clicked is
right there and where I'm painting over
everything is literally just duplicating
from over there and the reason I want to
do that because it maintains the um
coloration the same and the dots of the
way the ink hit the paper is largely the
same enough to where you can't it
becomes less obvious this was done
um this is actually a photo shoot
Photoshop technique by the way
even though I've never really used
Photoshop
so I'll get this cleared up here
so now I actually can set my thing over
here now it'll have more black area to
work from and I can now do this
I need someone let go this is going to
go back to beginning so I can do it like
a little bit and then it gets too close
to the letter A I can let go
repeat P repeat repeat
and as you can see this actually works
out pretty well
um I have to do something similar but
different
selections over for the next set of
words our next word
and if you're on Windows and Mac [ __ ] is
available to download and install you
have to um
look it up
White
now if I were to look at this really
close which I'll do just a second so you
can see
um it's not a perfect
um
it's usually flaws of some sort or
another in it but that's fine
see there's actually little spots of red
stuff let's find this totally harmless
because of my goal is just to get rid of
the English text while still maintaining
a general appearance of what the
original Comet looks like
now this one is a little bit differently
what I'll have to do over here is I'll
have to select
background
and then I'll have to do like this
very carefully
here you can see where it's actually
disappearing where it actually makes it
takes totally disappear
as if it never was there
yeah and I do have to periodically let
go of the mouse then press it back down
again
so that it keeps going back to the area
I'm trying to clone from
now this over here will probably work
out better
if I were to clone
um
the line itself so I'll line up here and
I'll control click to set the new clone
from point and then what I can do is
then I can just go up following the line
and keep letting go periodically
we need to do this lower
as you can see it's actually
allow me to do a line
I got to keep letting go periodically
and if I zoom in I can now get rid of
the stuff over here
get the um
free select tool we'll zoom in pretty
good so that we can draw better
all right so now we do not have any
English text the only thing I'm
interested in doing is I can see these
coloration variation which I a little
two more than I would like
so I'll go back to cloning
your adjustments there try to get it to
blend a little bit better
yes that'll work better all right
so now we gotta work on the book so file
save just in case things crash
so we need to do the same thing here so
I'll go ahead and
select let's see here
let's do here select as my source
and I can do a little bit at a time
because I don't have that much out of
the area I'm cloning from is not that
large I have to keep doing this a little
bit at a time
release in the mouse and clicking it
back
and here you can see it really doesn't
you really can't tell there was
something really there unless you really
look for any kind of minor distortions
in the background
in fact I don't need this black box at
all let's get rid of the whole Black Box
putting in a black box we can always add
it back we really don't have to have a
black box there
main thing we want to do is get a book
with a cover that we can then re-letter
using inkscape
so now we have a empty area for
um
putting new letter in this is kind of
lighter here on it I really don't want
to be more the same or you
a little bit
use a little bit more uniform feel
all right so this is the first page of
the comic
um
so I'm going to save it again
and then I'm going to go ahead and do
the remaining pages in a and you can see
it happen in fast mode
haha
okay now that we have the pages cleaned
up we need to crop them all
um based upon the visual information on
each page
so I'll go ahead and open them up one at
a time
and we'll pause away again works I go
ahead and open the rest of them up one
by one
so pretty much what we want is we're
wanting to get rid of all this Blank
Space
um so we're going to go to image
crop to content
you can see here it now has removed all
the extraneous blank space from around
the common
so I can save that close it and repeat
now here you will see like right here it
couldn't crop all the way it takes to
the Box because the gun is sticking
outside the box that's
happens a lot with comics
okay the next thing I'm going to do is
I'm going to create
um move all the xcf files
out of here
and I'm going to put them into a new
folder
call The Salty turtle
and because this is from issue 10 we're
going to put a 10 at the end
and then we're going to paste them into
here
okay so now these are the original hcfs
they still contain the transparency as
layers and other things needed for a
bitmap manipulation we need to convert
these into a format that we can load
into the inkscape program so I'm going
to open them back up again
um all of them
and I need to do a file
export as which is Ctrl shift e
and then I'm warning PNG right here so
it's got I gotta change it to dot PNG
and you make sure it's in my working
folder
and I'm going to hit export
and explore again
I do this for each of the images
all right so now we have
pngs for each of these images now
um keep things simpler one I'm going to
go ahead and create subfolders
this is going to be the um
uh Raw
images
we're gonna move everything into there
and I'll show you why in just a second
this way we're not confused so we got
all the raw images are in here
all right so here's I have the xcf
images I started off with that I cleaned
up this is the PNG versions which I need
the PNG versions for the generating the
actual uh for look for importing into
inkscape
and
um so I'm calling this raw images
because this is before I do any
lettering
so now
I need to activate inkscape inkscape is
also available for Windows and Mac
okay now the first thing I need to do is
change the paper size
um it's defaults to us letter for me I
mean it might be different for you so
you need to double check
as a general rule of thumb Comics are
not eight and a half by eleven even
though I put them away and have both of
them part of the time but if they're
Standalone I generally try to stick with
like six by nine
because it gets I mean it's not really
the correct aspiration for a true
comment which I think is like seven by
ten or something like that
um but this is close enough and and if
you're planning on doing print on demand
this is an available paper size you can
use for print on demand
so we're going to change the units back
to pixels
and then we can close this and so now we
have the 6x9
sheet and
internal this is going to be
um
page
189 I believe
okay so we got page 29. now I can go to
here
and
port and image doc
ument comics
I don't want the raw images and I want
to go ahead and get the first raw image
and so here it is and I'm going to hit
Ctrl shift a and we're going to center
it
actually does not fit the page so I need
to adjust this and I need them and I'll
need to record these numbers that I
adjust
so first thing we want to do is go and
change this to zero for the x coordinate
changes to zero for the y coordinate so
that it lines up with the top left
corner of the paper
[Music]
um
and then we need to add a margin
for the printing process
um 0.5 inches is usually pretty safe to
add so I'm adding 0.5 and 0.5 this way
and this way you can see how it moves
down
um
so this right here because it's uh six
what first I need to lock this
keep these two numbers mathematically
corrected with each other so six minus
one inch
so this would give a half an inch here
and a half an inch here and I can tell
it to recenter again so it's on the
centered on the paper so as you can see
it comic books
um don't exactly fit 6x9 but this is a
pretty uh close and this actually gives
you an option if you wanted to do extra
things at the top of the bottom you can
Okay so
now what we need to do is get the
document
contains the
um
um Cherokee language
translations
Okay so
amaha nadoxi
now doxy is really Terrapin and is not a
generic term for turtle
um just as an FYI so this is the title
which goes there so what I need to do
then is I need to go here I need to tell
I want to do text
then I need to tell it I want
um
Cherokee hand one
and I'm going to set this as my default
font
and they won't close that then we'll go
over here where it says the letter A
which is creating edit text boxes or
text objects
and I want to click here and I'm going
to write
um
in Cherokee
my writing
foreign
okay so this is going to be a fancy
graphic right here so I need to actually
use a different font
so okay so I'm looking at the different
font options we have available on the
cherokeelescence.com website so I can
see them all real quickly
and
let me see the Donnie said
might be decent let's take a look at
that
let's go down take a look
so what I want to do a fuse I want to
make sure you're
fill is white for the moment
cheer outline
in the stroked is black okay
so we'll move this over here
so the original one had text here and
text here
um
but we're not going to do it that way
we're going to do a like this
so we're going to click it again so I
get a little turning arrows I want to
rotate it
and then we'll click again and get the
stretchers
so I won't duplicate it
all that
Okay so
the original comic book
foreign
red and yellow
that seems decent
so we'll take this one
a little set to feel red
I'll take this one
let's set the fill to Yellow
now one of the things you have to be
really care about when you're doing
these translations is not to overflow
the text box with Cherokee text
sometimes this requires adjusting the
dialogue to fit the text the balloon
um
so again we're in Cherokee him one right
now we normally pick a fixed font size
for this
um so
the stroke I need to be nothing so I
want to set the stroke to nothing
set the field to be black
I'm gonna go here
I'm going to click right there
and it goes to go
the
D ski
um
yo
I'm not sure about you you old
okay let's do this again I don't want
true I don't want I want to feel
okay
and you can see this is a lot of texture
I stick in here
so I'm going to change the font
and it's usually best to try to keep the
font size consistent between
um
for the entire comic
all right
foreign
okay so there's the first page with the
Cherokee lettering added including the
book title and pretty much
all of the um
boxes of speech bubbles filled in now
one thing we do need to do is because
this is a transparency and this is a
transparency we need to add a white
background
um so that when we export this as an
image it has white
in the correct spots if we don't these
will turn transparent in the exported
image which is not what we want so
we know the size of the paper
which is 576 by 864.
in pixels
so what we want to do is we'll go over
here to box create rectangle square
we'll draw a rectangle
um
pretty much if you look at the bottom
you see where it says click to set fill
shift click to set stroke we don't want
a stroke
we want the field to be white
and then up here it's going to give you
some various options for the box but
these are not the options we want to
change what we need to do is hit the
select and transform option here
and this change as you can see the it
changes like this and then this becomes
the x coordinate and y coordinate on the
paper starting at the top left so zero
zeros here
so let's go ahead and move it there we
want to move the zero and zero so it's
at the top
and then we know the paper is
uh well first one okay this right here
um with this turned on if this number
changes this number changes the
proportional faction if you change this
number this number will change the
proportional fashion that's how you
prevent uh incorrect aspect ratio
stretching as you have this turned on if
you turn this off which is what we need
to do right now then it doesn't and then
it only uh impacts which one we type
into so we know that the paper is 576.
exactly and the height is exactly 864.
so now we have a a white box which is
the exact size of the paper
now I'm going to press the uh end button
while I got it highlighted
and that sends it to the background and
lets everything else be on the front
so now
I didn't type that right
576 864. yes so that's all right
is that
okay anyway that's the correct size so
now we have the complete image now when
you're
um
so the inkscape format cannot be
directly used in most programs and for
type setting and things you'll need to
change the formatting so what we'll need
to do is for ebooks and for print
generally they
generally prefer jpeg
but we have to do this as a two-step
process because inkscape only exports as
PNG so we'll export the PNG
first we want to do the entire page so
we get the page button right here that's
very very important you double check
that it's actually doing the page
then right here we have the DPI
um generally 300 DPI is good
um though it takes up more space
um
it's up here the exporting it's not down
here like I was expecting it
I guess now I can close that and I can
close this
now it's going to ask me to say to SVG
because I exported them go ahead and
save that too that way it keeps track of
the volume I used so here's the original
and I go to here right here all right so
this is the SVG we created this is the
inkscape file
and this PNG is what we exported out of
inkscape and as you can see
we now have an image of the comic
about the lettering put in place
now the only catch is because the amount
of text we're trying to fit into the
speech bubbles
we're using a slightly smaller than
desired font and it's a little bit light
on the type that's the only way to
really make it fit for this particular
translation
um and dialogue selection
so that pretty much covers how to take
images from an existing comic
and adjust it and clean it up a little
bit and then reloader it using [ __ ] and
inkscape when it comes to actually doing
the type setting it really depends on
what you're trying to accomplish
um if you're going through whether it's
ebook or paper you have to have a cover
image
which is appropriate to the content so
it's usually recommended to do most or
all of a complete comic depending upon
the how complex the content is that's
why you can use the original artwork and
adjust it with Cherokee writing from the
original cover
um
as far as software goes there are
different options if you're only wanting
to say go to Kindle
there's actually a special Kindle editor
which allows you to lay out fixed
formats like comic books you can
actually have it set up if you don't
mind doing all the extra work having it
where you can zoom into the individual
boxes and things like that in the Kindle
but it takes a bit of extra effort when
it comes to print format one program as
you can look at using is scribus as
c-r-i-b-u-s
um it's a page layout program designed
for laying things out on paper it's
really good it's supposed to be
professional grade and it's available at
no charge for multiple platforms as well
um another option depending upon your
needs is
um LibreOffice which can actually you
can actually use to create uh epubs with
um though I've never done that for
Comics to see whether it's how good or
bad the results are for like smash words
because smashwords has an automatic
conversion process where they'll convert
Microsoft Office docs to
ePub for you anything you can download
it and take a look at it
it also can handle the Libre office
which is a free product as well
there are various options including
typesetting languages like latex which
is what I generally use in combination
with a program called licks but that's
generally
for the more computer savvy individual
whereas a program like scribus
um and LibreOffice and things like that
are more oriented to
uh less technically Savvy when it comes
to actually needing to
do specific types of layout that are
actually needed in latex which is what I
use for
my general books it has lots of text in
them because I find the results better
than trying to do it manually because it
has a lot of automatic stuff you can use
but it's not really appropriate for
Comics per se
well I hope this helps and uh
don't let that go huh